A Guide to the James Edgar Chancellor Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #2181
Papers of James Edgar Chancellor 1847-1883
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
2181
7+ items
Miss Betty Cocke
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on June 6, 1945 by Miss Betty Cocke of Charlottesville.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of seven bound volumes, 1847-1883, mostly related to James Edgar Chancellor's medical education and service, and miscellaneous letters and papers. James Edgar Chancellor(1826-1896) was the son of George Chancellor and Ann (Lyon) Pound Chancellor of Spotsylvania County, Virginia. He had two brothers, Reverend Melzi Sanford Chancellor and Colonel Lorman Chancellor. He studied at Fredericksburg, Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia, and the University of Virginia(first session, 1846-47). He lived near Spotsylvania Court House until 1862 when he put his property up for sale and moved to Charlottesville where he practiced medicine at the Confederate States Army hospital. Some of the materials in this collection relate to his service as a surgeon in the Confederate States Army. He was also an instructor (Demonstrator of Anatomy) at the University of Virginia from the fall of 1865 until the spring of 1872.
Container List
- Bound Volumes
  - Medical and chemistry notebook from "Jefferson College", 1847 Nov-1848 Jan
    The instructor was Dr. Mitchell
  - Record book of surgical cases at Confederate States Army General Hospital, Charlottesville, 1862 June-1863 Nov
    Includes admissions after battles at Cedar Run and Manasses. Also includes medical lecture notes 1866, 1867, and 1870
  - Confederate States Army General Hospital, Charlottesville including admissions after Sharpsburg., 1862-1863
    Also included: Constitution and by-laws of the Mercer Cavalry, a cavalry corps attached to the 16th regiment, Virginia Militia, organized 1859. Membership list, officers, and minutes from meetings and musters, September 1860 to March 1861 at Spotsylvania courthouse.
  - Chemistry notebook and 1853 to 1861 memorandum book intermixed with chemistry and anatomy notes, 1865 Nov-1866 Jan
  - Medical notebook in "Minutes of the Session of the Presbyterian Church" volume., 1865-1866
  - Medical notebook, 1866, 1868, 1871
  - Chemistry notebook, University of Virginia, 1870 Nov-1871 Dec
- Miscellaneous letters and papers:
  - Warrenton, Va., from Johns S. Lindsay to William B. Thomas, 1872 April 2; ALS
  - Notification of election of officers of Hall of Widow's Son Lodge, No. 60, Charlottesville, 1872 May 18
  - Four identical photos of E.A. Chancellor, M.D., son of J.E. Chancellor, and a graduate of the University of Virginia, 1874 June
  - Lower Bremo, from Ida to Mattie, care of W.R.C. Cocke, Bremo Bluff, Fluvanna Co., 1883 April 8; ALS,
  - Envelopes, n.d.
- Oversize items:
  - Certificate of membership for J. E. Chancellor in the Missionary Society of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, 1856 December 10
  - Albemarle Colportage and Sunday School Society annual meeting report, 1871 November 15
  - Clipping from Baltimore American regarding the first international Sunday School Convention, 1875 May 14
  - Certificate of membership (blank) Virginia Conference Sunday School Society of the Methodist Episcopal Church South